Let us consider a system with an ideal gas
in it.
The state of the gas, or more precisely, its
temperature T, its pressure Pi and its volume
V are described by the ideal gas equation:
Pi is equal to n times R times T times 1 divided
by V. n is the amount of substance and indirectly
describes the number of gas particles and
R is the gas constant.
We refer to temperature, pressure and volume
as properties - they describe the macroscopic
state of the gas.
If we heat the gas and thus increase its temperature
T, we are talking about a thermodynamic process.
We could also compress the gas, thereby increasing
the pressure and reducing the volume - this
would also be a thermodynamic process.
The thermodynamic process can be isobaric,
isothermal, isochoric or adiabatic.
In the case of an isobaric process, the pressure
of the gas remains constant.
This means that Pi, n and R are pure constants
in the gas law and the volume V is proportional
to the temperature T.
The pressure-volume diagram results in a horizontal
straight line for an isobaric gas.
This means that a change in volume does NOT
lead to a change in gas pressure.
The volume V of the gas remains constant during
an isochoric process.
Then V, n and R are constants in the gas law,
and the pressure Pi is proportional to the
temperature T.
The pressure-volume diagram shows a vertical
straight line for an isochoric gas.
The change in gas pressure does NOT lead to
a change in volume.
In an isothermal process, the temperature
T of the gas remains constant.
This means that the pressure Pi is proportional
to the inverse volume: 1 by V.
The pressure-volume diagram shows a decreasing
curve for an isothermally behaving gas.
Increasing the volume of the gas leads to
a reduction in the gas pressure.
During an adiabatic process, no thermal energy
is transported OUT and into the system.
During this thermodynamic process, the temperature
T, volume V and pressure Pi of the gas can
change simultaneously.
The pressure-volume diagram shows a power
law for an adiabatically behaving gas.
The exponent gamma is referred to as the adiabatic
exponent.